Guide to the John Howard Griffin Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
John Howard Griffin Papers,
1920-1980
Griffin, John Howard, 1920-1980.
18 linear feet (37 document boxes).
Columbia University. Rare book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
6749110
Biographical Note
John Howard Griffin (1920-1980) was born in Mansfield, Texas. His early training was as a musicologist in Tours, France specializing in Gregorian Chant. He studied psychology, specializing in the effects of music on the mentally disturbed. He also studied photography and became an expert portrait photography.
During WWII he help Jews in France escape the Nazis. After the fall of France, he joined the U. S. Army Air Corps and was sent to the South Pacific to work with the native islanders. Injured by a bomb blast he gradually lost his sight, becoming totally blind by 1947. During his blindness he wrote his two major novels The Devil Rides Outside and Nuni as well as numerous short stories. In 1951 he became a Roman Catholic. After recovering his sight in 1957, he wrote for Sepia magazine and in 1959 he wrote a series of articles for Sepia magazine based on his travels through the Deep South as a "black" man. This series was published as Black Like Me in 1961.
In 1969 he was appointed the Official Biographer of Thomas Merton. Throughout his life he wrote and lectured widely on race relation and social justice. He died in 1980 at the age of sixty.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, documents, photographs, and printed materials by and about John Howard Griffin. The correspondence is extensive and includes letter from Jacques Maritain; Thomas Merton; Maxwell Geismar; Eldridge Cleaver; Robert Casadeus; Abraham Rattner; P.D. East; Joseph Noonan; Sarah Patton Boyle; Lillian Smith; Father August Thompson; Nell Dorr; and Brother Patrick Hart. All of his major works are represented in manuscript form (usually typescript, carbon). In addition there are many original photographs by Griffin, which he pasted throughout his extensive journal, 1950-1980. This journal is a remarkable account of his life and thoughts, extending to over 3,000 pages
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 20 series:
Series I: The Early Years: 1920-1947
Series II: The Devil Rides Outside
Series III: Shorter Writings, 1950s
Series IV: Nuni; Street Of The Seven Angels; Passagaglia
Series V: Land Of The High Sky
Series VI: The Decade Of the Fifties
Series VII: General Correspondence, 1949-1980
Series VIII: Black Like Me
Series IX: Personal Essays and Journalism
Series X: The Church and The Black Man
Series XI. Scattered Shadows and The John Howard Griffin Reader
Series XII. The Decade Of The Sixties
Series XIII: The Thomas Merton File
Series XIV. A Hidden Wholeness and Follow The Ecstasy
Series XV. The Jacques Maritain File
Series XVI. A Time To Be Human
Series XVII. The Decade Of The Seventies
Series XVIII The Hermitage Journals
Series XIX. The Griffin Journal, 1950-1980
Series XX. Posthumous Papers
Series XXI. Photographs
Series XXII: Photographs by Others
Subjects
Columbia University.; Lionel Trilling Seminars.; Anderson, Quentin, 1912-2003.; Anderson, Maxwell, 1888-1959.; Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1803-1882--Criticism and interpretation.; James, Henry, 1843-1916--Criticism and interpretation.; Trilling, Lionel, 1905-1975.; American literature--History and criticism.; Criticism--United States.; Education--Study and teaching--United States.; Literature and society.; Articles.; Card files.; Correspondence.; Drafts (literary).; Essays.; Journals.; Lectures.; Manuscripts (literary).; Notes.; Reviews.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Mrs. Thelma Anderson, Gift, June 2004 (with a subsequent addition in May 2005).
- Series I: The Early Years: 1920-1947
  - Biographical Sketch, (8 page t.m.s. (incomplete) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bibliography of Books and Monographs, (5 page t.ms.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Texas Department of Health Birth Certificate, (1 page (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Coat of Arms and Genealogy, (1 page each (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Moliere Les Femmes Savantes, Paris: Librairie Hachette, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    [Inscribed "Howard Griffin, Lyc e Descartes"
  - American Conservatory Certificate of Attendance, [Paris], 1946, (1 page (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Griffin, John Howard Handbook for Darkness, [Mansfield, TX], 1948, (34 page t.ms.) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    [Griffin's study "especially prepared for those who are in close contact with the blind". The text covers such areas as: "What Blindness Should Be to the Blind." "The Role of Those Who Live with the Blind." "The Role of Fear." "Potentialities for Overcoming the Handicap Ways to Financial Independence." "Marriage and Children." "The Intimate Life." "Religion." Plus notes for mini chapters on Interests, Travel, A House Guest, A Hotel Guest, Clerks in Stores, and Mechanical Aids. Unpublished. The text's last six pages contain a series of "Observations on. Blindness and Suggestions for Those Who See," which are short, compelling remarks that sum up his philosophy most effectively.
  - Griffin, John Howard Review of Jacob Twersky's Blindness in Literature, The American Foundation for the Blind., [1948], (3 page t.ms. (carbon) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    [There is no record of this manuscript having been published
  - Defense Passive Convocation, Tours, France, 30 September 1939, (One 5" x 8" sheet Mimeograph document, with notes in pencil) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Defense Passive "Les Gaz de Combat", (Two 8 1/2" x ll" sheets Mimeograph document, with notes in pencil) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    [Penciled notes are not in Griffin's handwriting
  - Comite International de la Croix-Rouge To Howard Griffin, Geneva, 13 September 1939, (1 t.l., signed by Mlle. L. Odier, Membre due Comite International (and) Membre de la Commission des Oeuvres de Guerre) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tours. School of Medicine Diploma awarded to John Howard Griffin, Tours, 17 May 1946, (1 page (photostat) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - United State of America. Army Military record and certificate of honorable discharge of John Howard Griffin, [n.p.], 1945, (3 pages (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - United State of America. Department of State Passport of John Howard Griffin, Texas, 26 June 1946, (6 page (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Father Marie-Bruno, O.P. [Andre Hussar] To John Howard Griffin, [v.p.], 1 May 1945 - 19 May 1947, (10 a.l.s. 1 autograph saint card) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    [Monk and spiritual mentor to John Howard Griffin
  - Casadesus, Robert To John Howard Griffin, [v.p.], 1941-1952, (18 a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    [French pianist and composer; musical mentor to John Howard Griffin. Five posted from Princeton, NJ; two on letterhead of the School of Music, American Art Schools of Fontainebleau; others posted from concert stops in St. Louis, Cleveland, and Miami; 25 pages (front and back combined); and four Autograph Envelopes
  - Casadesus, Robert To Whom It May Concern, Palace of Fontainebleau, France, 28 May 1964, (1 a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    [With photocopy of t.l., signed by Claude Levi-Strauss, French Ambassador and Minister of Culture, concerning Griffin's acceptance to study music; t.l., signed by Mary Crennan. on Columbia Concerts letterhead to Griffin, regarding his query as to Casadesus' concert schedule, November 30, 1945
  - Casadesus, Jean To John Howard Griffin, New York, [17 April 1972], (1 t.n.s.) (Box 1, Folder 18)
    [With a carbon letter from Griffin to Jean Casadesus, July 28, 1963; form Letter of the Robert Casadesus Society to Griffin, signed by Therese Casadesus-Rawson, for the Organizing Committee; November 24, 1974 -Carbon of Typed Letter from Griffin to Therese Casadesus-Rawson, concerning his memory of her as the childhood daughter of Gaby and Robert Casadesus during which she nicknamed him le grand ours, November 30, 1974
  - Treverton, James R. News Feature published in the St. Louis Globe-Democrat, 11 Nov. 1943, based on an interview with Gaby Casadesus, pianist and wife of Robert Casadesus. Anecdotes about their friend and neighbor at Princeton, Albert Einstein; St. Louis Symphony conductor Vladimir Golschmann; the musical progress of the Casadesus children -- News Photo from an unknown and undated New York newspaper, concerning a concert to be given by the Casadesus for Russian War Relief, at Carnegie Hall -- Obituaries from the New York Times and the New York Post. Casadesus died 19 September 1972, after an operation for cancer of the pancreas; he was 73, 1943-1972, (4 clippings) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Casadesus, Robert Four Music Programs, including one autographed by the pianist -- Photocopies of Two other Music Programs--one of the Casadesus Family (Robert, Gaby, and Jean) and the other of a concert by Gaby Casadesus and Pierre Bernac, tenor, [n.p.], 1941-1946, (7 items ) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Robert Casadesus: Four sheets of promotional material and news from the Robert Casadesus Society, including envelope addressed to John Howard Griffin -- Brochure for the Jean Casadesus Memorial Fund, Department of Music, State University of New York at Binghamton -- Article in Musical America, discussing the first Ravel/Casadesus International Piano Competition, held at the Cleveland Institute of Music, August 25-31, 1975; the December 1975 piece includes a photograph of Gaby Casadesus and winner John Owings, [n.p.], 1972-1980, (4 items) (Box 1, Folder 21)
    [Jean Casadesus was pianist-in-residence at SUNY, from 1965 until his death in January of 1972, in an automobile accident; he was 44
  - Reverdy, Pierre To John Howard Griffin, [Solesmes, France], 23 November 1953, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 22)
    [In French. French poet, close friend of Picasso, Braque, etc.; he died in 1961.
  - Szigeti, Joseph To John Howard Griffin, Eugene, OR, 15 January 1945, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 23)
    [World-renowned violinist
  - Rheiny, Arthur To John Howard Griffin, Solesmes, France, 21 January 1948, (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 24)
    [In French
  - Reynal, Maurice To John Howard Griffin, Paris, 25 April 1949, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Rattner, Abraham To John Howard Griffin, New York, 1943/1944, (18 a.l.s., 1 a.n.s., 1 telegram, 6 clippings, articles, etc.) (Box 1, Folder 26-30)
    [American painter who studied in Paris where he became friends with the Cubists and Surrealists. These letters were written in 1943 and 1944 while Griffin was a Sergeant in the Air Force 424 Bomber Squadron, serving in the South Pacific. The letters written from 1945 to 1949 cover the years of Griffin's return from the war, preparations for a trip to France (where he delivered packages of clothing for Rattner to the artist's friends in France), and also Griffin's return from France to live on a farm in Mansfield, Texas (then completely blind).
  - Gentle, Esther To John Howard Griffin, [New York], [12 May 1975], (1 a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Series II: The Devil Rides Outside
  - Griffin, John Howard The Devil Rides Outside, [n.p.], Christmas 1949, (587 pp. t.ms. (carbon), In 12 folders) (Box 1, Folder 32-43)
    [The first draft of Griffin's first novel. Sent as a gift to Sally Gillespie. In reading the manuscript it becomes obvious that the news stories surrounding the novel's composition--stories which were promulgated by the Smith brothers who owned Smiths, Inc. of Fort Worth--were inaccurate: Griffin did not write a 900 plus page manuscript which was cut nearly one-third by the editor/publisher Gordon Smith; the novel did not begin as a non-fiction account of Griffin's experience at the Abbey of Solemes, the Benedictine motherhouse of Gregorian Chant.. The novel varies from the final Smiths published version in relatively minor ways. It does not open with the scene of the anonymous American musicologist being driven to the old monastery by the cab driver, but begins with the narrator in his monastic cell (which is the second scene of the published version). The original manuscript has a short Epilogue which was dropped from the published book. That Epilogue was Part III, whereas the book has only two parts, entitled ."The Cloister Within" and "The Devil Without". The original manuscript simply calls these first two parts, "The Monastery" and. "The Village." Otherwise, the manuscript runs closely to the published book. This does not indicate Griffin made several complete drafts from this 1947 first draft to the galley stage, in 1951. (The novel was published in 1952). It indicates that some sections were added later and some cutting was done from the original manuscript. The massive, poorly-written, obscenity-riddled typescript of 900 pages is a fiction of the publisher. Also, the press releases from The Smiths which referred to Griffin's blindness and his war heroics were considered in bad taste by the author. He preferred to use a pseudonym which he had used (several in fact) when he submitted magazines work. Several pieces were published under the name Lew Smollett and no mention of the author's blindness or war experiences were included. Griffin discusses these times in his letters to Sally Gillespie (see Series VII)
  - Daniels, Brad Background notes about the The Devil Rides Outside and its subsequent censorship case, [n.p.], [1968], (7 page (photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Feature articles from Texas newspapers prior to the publication of The Devil Rides Outside, Texas, 1952, (9 page (photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Reviews of The Devil Rides Outside in Time; Saturday Review; NY Herald Tribune; Dallas Times-Herald; Fort Worth Star-Telegram and other national publications, [v.p.], 1952, (28 page (photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Griffin, John Howard Article on the censorship of The Devil Rides Outside, Dallas Morning News, 1954, (1 page (photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Fadiman, Clifton To John Howard Griffin, Mansfield, Texas, 30 Aug. [n.y.], (1 t.l. (copy) (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Sussman, Cornelia and Irving How To Read A Dirty Book, Franciscan Herald Press, [n.d.], (1 dust jacket, 5 page (photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 49)
    [Pages 102 - 111 of the book [Missing after exhibit]
  - News stories about the censorship case, Detroit News and the Detroit Free Press, 1954, (26 page (photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Gerber, Albert B. Sex, Pornography and Justice, New York: Lyle Stuart, 1965, (9 page (photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 51)
    [Legal discussion of the Butler vs. Michigan case (Griffin's novel was the focus of a test case put forth by Pocket Books, publisher of the paperback Devil)
  - Griffin, John Howard To Father Gardiner, Mansfield, Texas, 26 June 1956, (1 a.l. (carbon), 2 pages) (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Griffin, John Howard To The Editor, The Michigan Catholic, [Texas], 29 July 1954, (1 t.l. (carbon), 4 pages) (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Griffin, John Howard To Father Maino, [Texas], 15 August 1954, (1 t.l. (carbon), 9 pages) (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Griffin, John Howard To Father Maino, [Texas], 7 October 1954, (1 t.l. (carbon), 8 pages) (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Griffin, John Howard To Reverend Jobert J. Dwyer, [Texas], 13 August 1956, (1 t.l. (copy), 4 pages) (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Griffin, John Howard To Paschal Varnskuhler, [Texas], 16 August 1956, (1 t.l. (copy), 4 pages) (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Owens, Robert To John Howard Griffin, Denver and Anderson, SC, 9 April 1965 - 17 January 1966, (3 t.l.s.) (Box 2, Folder 58)
    [Re. playscript of Devil
  - Marshall, Bruce Statement on The Devil Rides Outside, [n.p.], 14 October 1953, (1 t.l. (copy) (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Pocket Books, Inc. To John Howard Griffin, New York, 7 May 1964, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 2, Folder 60)
    [With two related letters concerning a Polish edition of The Devil Rides Outside
  - Presses de la Cite & Smiths, Inc. Promotional materials for The Devil Rides Outside, [v.p.], ca. 1952, (5 items) (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Houghton Mifflin To John Howard Griffin, Boston, 1 April & 22 July 1969, (2 t.l.s., 3 t.l. (carbon replies) (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Smith, J. Hulbert To John Howard Griffin, Fort Worth, 1 April & 22 July 1969, (2 t.l.s., 3 t.l. (carbon replies) (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Canadian Broadcasting Corp. To Elizabeth Bonazzi, Toronto, 1985, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 2, Folder 64)
    [Regarding reading from Devil
  - Alexandrian Press To John Howard Griffin Estate, CA, 1984, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 2, Folder 65)
    [Requisition to reprint Devil
  - Southern Methodist University Press To Robert Bonazzi, Dallas, Texas, 1987, (3 t.l.s.) (Box 2, Folder 66)
    [ Regarding reprinting The Devil Rides Outside
- Series III: Shorter Writings 1950s
  - Griffin, John Howard "The Cage", Mansfield, Texas, [n.d.], (21 page t.ms. (carbon) (Box 2, Folder 67)
    [Dedicated to Abraham Rattner
  - Griffin, John Howard "The Peas", Mansfield, Texas, [1951?], (23 page t.ms. (with ms. corrections) (Box 2, Folder 68)
    [About a young boy growing up blind on a farm. This is a more successful reworking of "The Cage". It was submitted to magazines 1951-1953 (unpublished)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Scraps for a Feast" ["The Seawall"], Mansfield, Texas, [1955?], (13 page t.ms.) (Box 2, Folder 69)
    [Fictional rendering of an actual trip Griffin made to Galveston (unpublished)
  - Griffin, John Howard "The Seawall", Mansfield, Texas, [1952], (13 page t.ms. (with ms. corrections) (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Black Noon", Mansfield, Texas, [1952], (5 page t.ms.) (Box 2, Folder 71)
    [Vignette about blind man going to town (unpublished)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Just Ask Wooly", Catholic Digest, November 1956, (7 page photocopy (incomplete) (Box 2, Folder 72)
    [Reprint of story that appeared originally in Catholic World.
  - Griffin, John Howard "Blindness - what it is and what problems it entails.", [n.p.], May 1959, (2 page t.ms. ) (Box 2, Folder 73)
    [Lecture outline
  - Smollett, Lew "The Big-Time Stockman", Farm and Ranch, February 1952, (2 page photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 74)
    [Story about blind farm boy who raises livestock. Griffin's first published short story
  - Gantz, H. L. "Trouble is what you make it", Farm and Ranch, [n.d.], (2 page photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 75)
    [Profile of Griffin. Reveals that Lew Smollett is really Griffin
  - Daniel, Bradford Notes on Griffin's short stories, [n.p.], [1967], (3 page photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Withdrawal of the Artist", The Nation, May 1953, (1 page photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 77)
    [On being a writing member of the Silent Generation
  - Griffin, John Howard Review of Bonner McMillion's The Lot of Her Neighbors, The Daily Times Herald, March 1953, (1 page photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Sauce for the Gander", New York: New American Library, 1953, (10 page photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Griffin, John Howard Reprint of "Sauce for the Gander", New York: Macmillan, 1956, (8 page photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Friar Clud", [Mansfield, Texas], [1953], (10 page t.ms. (with ms. corrections) (Box 2, Folder 81)
    [Unpublished
  - Griffin, John Howard "Friar Clud", [Mansfield, Texas], [1953], (33 page t.ms. (incomplete, with ms. corrections) (Box 2, Folder 82)
    [Unpublished. Sequel to "Sauce for the Gander"
  - Griffin, John Howard "Metamorphosis", [Mansfield, Texas], [n.d.], (11 page t.ms. (missing page 1) (Box 2, Folder 83)
    [ Third draft. Unpublished short story which is reminiscent of The Devil Rides Outside in that it takes place in a monastery and portrays similar monk characters
  - "Metamorphosis", [Mansfield, Texas], [n.d.], (3 page t.ms. (carbon) (Box 2, Folder 84)
    [2nd draft?
  - Griffin, John Howard "Metamorphosis", [Mansfield, Texas], [n.d.], (3 page t.ms.) (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Roadblock", Mansfield, Texas, [1950s], (54 page t.ms. (with ms. corrections) (Box 2, Folder 86)
    [Short story about working in the French Underground based on Griffin's actual experience
  - Griffin, John Howard "Roadblock", [Mansfield, Texas], [n.d.], (14 page t.ms. (playscript) (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Samuel Mullins's Unfortunate Jinx", [Mansfield, Texas], [n.d.], (29 page t.ms (carbon, with ms. corrections) (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Samuel Mullins's Unfortunate Jinx", Mansfield, Texas, [n.d.], (28 page t.ms. (carbon) (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Samuel Mullins's Unfortunate Jinx", Mansfield, Texas, [n.d.], (20 page t.ms.) (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Samuel Mullins's Unfortunate Jinx", Mansfield, Texas, [n.d.], (19 page t.ms.) (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Griffin, John Howard "The Bargain", [Mansfield, Texas], [n.d.], (8 page t.ms.) (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Model Boy", [Mansfield, Texas], [n.d.], (14 page t.ms. (carbon)First draft(?) (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Griffin, John Howard "The Weakling" [Model Boy], [Mansfield, Texas], [n.d.], (14 page t.ms. (carbon) (Box 2, Folder 94)
    [2nd draft(?)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Southern Dirge in Black and White" [Model Boy], Mansfield, Texas, [n.d.], (13 page t.ms.) (Box 2, Folder 95)
    [3rd draft(?)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Miss Henrietta Briggs and Her Metamorphosis", Story Number Three, The Magazine of the Short Story in Book Form, 1953, (16 page photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - "Clovis's Thirst", [Mansfield, Texas], [n.d.], (10 page t.ms.) (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Noble Vision", Mansfield, Texas, [n.d.], (20 page t.ms. (carbon, with ms. corrections) (Box 2, Folder 98)
    [Early draft of "The Cause" a story published in The John Howard Griffin Reader
  - "The Whole World in His Hands", New York: New Voices 2, 1955, (12 page photocopy) (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Griffin, John Howard "Afternoon Hooch", Mansfield, Texas, [1953], (15 page t.ms., (with autograph corrections) (Box 3, Folder 100)
    [Unpublished. Based on a 1953 trip to the Bowery with Clyde Holland
  - Griffin, John Howard "Diversions", [Mansfield, Texas], [1955-1957], (12 page t.ms. (with ms. corrections) (Box 3, Folder 101)
    [Humorous vignettes, published in The John Howard Griffin Reader
  - Griffin, John Howard More "Diversions", [Mansfield, Texas], [ca. 1955], (10 p, t.ms.) (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Lamfamboise, Jean-Charles "Pontifical Teaching and the Christian Family". Translated from the French by Griffin, [Mansfield, Texas], 1956, (10 page t.ms.(carbon) (Box 3, Folder 103)
    [Also a copy of a letter from Father Lamfamboise and an offprint of the original French text.. Besides translating his own fiction from the French, Griffin spoke both of his novels, The Devil Rides Outside and Nuni, into a wire-recorder, in French, and then transcribed the novels into English. He translated various other French texts. Few were published but he made these translations as much to keep himself bilingual and for the intrinsic value of what he translated. During this period he was also receiving tapes, in both English and French, from Jacques Maritain, Father Stanley Murphy, and Gerald Vann, the British Dominican scholar. He considered it all part of his continuing classical education in language, in philosophy, and in theology. He speaks also of translating some of Albert Camus' novel The Stranger into English, but none of those pages have been found. In his Journals there are various letters and short texts translated into English for his own purposes.
  - Griffin, John Howard "Nuestra Senora de la Resurreccion", Mansfield, Texas, [n.d.], (9 page t.ms. (carbon) (Box 3, Folder 104)